<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Anti-Brekekekex-Coax-Coax, or, A throat-hapse for the frogges and toades that lately crept abroad, croaking against the Common-prayer book and Episcopacy and the copie of a letter from a very reverend church-man, in answer to a young man, who desired his judgement upon this case, viz. whether every minister of the Church of England be bound in conscience to reade the Common-prayer : with another letter from a convinced associatour, that a while boggled at the Common-prayer, to a brother of the same association, not yet convinced, together with the above-said reverend person's brief and candid censure thereupon, with some uses of application by the publisher.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3483A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475007</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75462)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2243:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Anti-Brekekekex-Coax-Coax, or, A throat-hapse for the frogges and toades that lately crept abroad, croaking against the Common-prayer book and Episcopacy and the copie of a letter from a very reverend church-man, in answer to a young man, who desired his judgement upon this case, viz. whether every minister of the Church of England be bound in conscience to reade the Common-prayer : with another letter from a convinced associatour, that a while boggled at the Common-prayer, to a brother of the same association, not yet convinced, together with the above-said reverend person's brief and candid censure thereupon, with some uses of application by the publisher.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 [i.e. 36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in hopes to doe good to the publick, or at least to give some check to the impudent slanders of some malicious non-conformists, who by the same artifice, as they did in the year 1642, goe about to re-inflame these nations by their libellous pamphlets,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151108:1"/>
            <p>AN Anti-Brekekekex-Coax-Coax. OR A THROAT-HAPSE FOR THE FROGGES AND TOADES That lately Crept abroad, Croaking againſt the Common-prayer-Book AND EPISCOPACY. AND The Copie of a LETTER from a very Reverend CHURCH-MAN, in Anſwer to a young man, who deſired his Judgement upon this Caſe, <hi>viz. Whether every Miniſter of the</hi> CHURCH <hi>of ENGLAND be bound in Conſcience to reade the Common-prayer?</hi> With Another LETTER from a Convinced Aſſociatour, that a while boggled at the Common-prayer, to a Brother of the ſame Aſſociation, not yet convinced; together with the above-ſaid Reverend Perſon's Brief and candid Cenſure thereupon; with ſome Uſes of Application by the Publiſher.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed, in hopes to doe good to the Publick, or at leaſt to give ſome check to the Impudent Slanders of ſome Malicious Non-Conformiſts, who by the ſame Artifice, as they did in the Year 1642, goe about to re-inflame theſe Nations by their Libellous Pamphlets. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151108:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151108:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Munday</hi> September 24. 1660.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His night about eleven of the clock, was a very violent fire in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> which began at the Red Lion, in a ſhort time conſumed many houſes, and did in a manner ſurround the dwelling houſe of the Reverend Doctor <hi>Wilde,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>London Derry</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> did fiercely blaze againſt the walls thereof, being but of a thin Flemmiſh building, and even into the very windows of ſundry rooms: And yet God was pleaſed miraculouſly to preſerve the ſaid houſe, and there to give a ſtop to the fire, as he had done ſome years ſince at the ſame Doctor's houſe; which is a ſufficient confutation, if there were no other, of that ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and Phanatick Pamphlet lately ſet forth, as a little The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atre of God's judgements againſt ſuch as have been forward to Revive the uſe of the Common-prayer book. 'Tis well known that the ſaid Doctor <hi>Wilde,</hi> all along theſe horrid confuſions, and even in the heighth of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Tyranny, did conſtantly uphold and practiſe, as became a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Liturgy of the ſaid Church. And who can tell (though it be indeed an high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption for any to be too determinate in judging of God's providences, and prying into his cabinet counſels) yet I ſay, who can tell, but that even for a Teſtimony to theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and this great City eſpecially, of God's gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of the appointed Liturgies and Letanies of our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151108:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>poor perſecuted Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> God hath been pleaſed twice ſo remarkably to preſerve that houſe and family, where his worſhip hath been ſo regularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. And if one would be a little induſtrious to muſter the diſaſters of thoſe that have been adverſaries to Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, and the eſtabliſhed diſcipline and Liturgy, it were no great taske, nor altogether unſeaſonable for theſe giddy times.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>As for example.</head>
               <p>The ſudden taking off Mr. <hi>Gower</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> within few dayes after his coming up to <hi>London,</hi> with the Petition of many aſſociated non-conformiſts, intruders, &amp;c. of thoſe parts.</p>
               <p>Of the ſudden and dangerous rupture of body that not long ſince befell Mr. <hi>Bampfield</hi> of <hi>Sherborn Dorſet,</hi> and the various miſchiefs that have fallen upon him, and his aſsiſtant forſooth (for Curate is grown too low a title) <hi>viz.</hi> The ejection of the latter out of his uſurped fellowſhip in Saint <hi>Magdalen's</hi> Colledge, <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſudden death of both of their horſes, on which they were wont to ride to aſſociations, unlawfull faſts and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; cauſed as is ſhrewdly ſuſpected by three or four of their own Diſciples, that pretended to be great Converts of their making, but are now under ſuſpition and legal reſtraint for witches.</p>
               <p>Of ſo many ſcores of intruders, that for recovery of their Hypochondriack maladies, or elſe to waſh off, if it were poſsible by water-drinking, the ſtaines of their conſciences, for the coveting and violent poſſeſsing of their neighbours, nay their own Mother's ſons houſes and lands, at the late famous waters at <hi>Woodbury</hi> hill, <hi>Dorſet:</hi> Their own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151108:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſons, I ſay, and Fathers two, unleſs they be baſtards, which 'tis to be feared too many of them be; and the worſt of baſtards, an inceſtuous brood, being generated, not by any Father or Biſhop of the Church; but in the heat of a ſchiſmaticall luſt, by their own brother Presbyters.</p>
               <p>Of the great infirmity of body and mind which Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> hath been ſubject to, ever ſince he was preſent and acceſſary to the plundring of <hi>Sherborn</hi>-ſchool and Almes houſe.</p>
               <p>Of the exceeding great weakneſs of Mr. <hi>Forde</hi> of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> ſince his recanting his recantation, and declaiming ſo vehemenly againſt Biſhops and common-prayer.</p>
               <p>Of the grievous affliction, Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi> of <hi>Exceſter</hi> hath had, with his eldeſt daughter, who was firſt mazed with his over-auſtere looks, his thundring doctrines of abſolute predeſtination and reprobation, and his extravagant zeal, or choller rather, againſt the old Epiſcopacy and Liturgy; and continues a great affliction to him; God of his mercy look upon her, and in her converſion convert her Father and her other relations, to a due obedience to the Laws of God, of the King, and the Church.</p>
               <p>Of Mr. <hi>Chetwyn</hi> of <hi>VVells</hi> his ſad diſtemper, ſince his being ſo great a Phanatick and Stickler for <hi>Extempore</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and againſt the old orders of the Church.</p>
               <p>Of the ill ſucceſſes of all the intruding fellows of Saint <hi>Magdalens</hi> Colledge <hi>Oxon.</hi> Since their diviſion of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Toloſanum,</hi> the good founder's gold, by their little leſs then ſacrilegious avarice, and their rending of the Church by their Chappell chat, and Saint <hi>Marie's</hi> Sermons.</p>
               <p>Of Mr. <hi>Ben</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſters</hi> monſtrous chin-cough, which would make any that hears him, doubt theres a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151108:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhrewd core at his conſcience, for his ſubſcribing to the Kings tryall, and outing Mr. <hi>Newt</hi> at <hi>Tiverton,</hi> to make room for his ſon and daughter <hi>Polewheel,</hi> and other hainous crimes, beſides his great ſlip at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that all his Hah-hings cannot remove.</p>
               <p>Of young Mr. <hi>Tomlins</hi> of <hi>Newbury,</hi> who was in armes againſt Biſhops and Common prayer, and ſadly cut his own throat.</p>
               <p>Of the impure daughter of that old factious Puritan, <hi>Gervaſe</hi> of <hi>Andover,</hi> who firſt got a great belly among her holy brethren, as they call them, and then to hide the ſhame of the ungodlike godly, ungratiouſly hang'd her ſelf in her Father's barn, and yet was buried in thoſe ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied times in the Church-yard, as if ſhe had dyed a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian death, whereas yet neither King nor Church are ſatisfied for her <hi>Felo de ſe</hi> out of that eſtate ſhe dyed poſſeſſed of.</p>
               <p>Of two of Captain <hi>Doweys</hi> ſouldiers that likewiſe hanged themſelves in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> rather then they would live to hear or ſay, Almighty and moſt mercifull Father, we have erred and ſtraied.</p>
               <p>Of the famous Mr. <hi>Obadiah Sedgewick</hi> of <hi>Covent-garden.</hi> that after his exceſsive venery, now and anon two, turn'd mere Sot.</p>
               <p>Of Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> of <hi>Northampton,</hi> that turned worſe then Sot; which may ſerve to put in the ſcales againſt that baſe ſlaunder of the ingenious Mr. <hi>John Ball</hi> late fellow of <hi>Wadham</hi> Colledge, that, in the book of the Toades, is ſaid to have been ſuddenly ſtruck for his having acted a part in a Comedy, in deriſion of an old puritan; whereas the ſaid Comedy was onely to repreſent the extravagancies of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151108:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>love, and was performed chiefly to gratifie the honourable and hopefull Baronet Sir <hi>VViliam Portman,</hi> vvho vvith all that were preſent, God be thanked, are yet in perfect health ſave onely Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> vvho in a journey aftervvard in the exceeding hot vveather, took a ſurfet by eating Pork and Caule, and thereof dyed: and to give him his due now he is gone, 'tis fit to be known that he was the Son of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Presbyterian and Non-conformiſt, and ſo are moſt of his relations; and in that way and thoſe ſchiſmaticall principles he was bred: yet being a very good ſchollar, and after his coming to <hi>Oxford,</hi> reading indifferently the books of both ſides, and ſeriouſly weighing their ſcriptures, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and reaſons, forſook the Presbyterians, and freely and chearfully came over to the Epiſcopall judgement, even in thoſe times when there was not the leaſt glimps of hope of his advantaging but rather blaſting his preferments by ſo doing.</p>
               <p>And of ſundry the like notorious afflictions upon diverſe Miniſters and other Non-conformiſts, in ſundry Counties.</p>
               <p>It would make up a far larger book then that wherein the Army of the Toads is ſo ridiculouſly ſet forth, and that not ſo much to ſhevv the judgements of God againſt the revivers of Common prayer, as of Quakers and other ſuch Phanaticks and ſectaries, as any but mere dolts may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, in diverſe particulars of that book: however the title page layes all on the Common prayers ſcore. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the old ones Maxime, <hi>calumniare fortiter, aliquid hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebit,</hi> caſt dirt enough, and ſome of it will ſtick on the ſmootheſt and pureſt wall or garment.</p>
               <p>Perhaps ſome will ſay, Doctor <hi>Brownrig,</hi> who was for Epiſcopacy and Common prayer, died of a ſudden extream
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151108:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>fit of the ſtone, the ſcholars or hard ſtudents diſeaſe; but <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> who is againſt both, is hang'd, drawn and quarterd according to Law, pray which is the greater judgement, the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> who was for both, died of the ſmall pox, for which ſome vile wretches have kept a thankſgiving day, with words to this purpoſe, Lord, as thou haſt cut off one of the limbs of that wicked family, to go on to deſtroy it root and branch, till there be not one of that wicked race left; but <hi>Henry Martine,</hi> who was againſt both, either is already dead, or like to die of the great, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called the French or Gallick Pox, to ſave the hangman a labour, I pray, which is the greater judgement?</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee how eaſie it is to accumulate undeniable Paradigmes, more then a good many, of ſuch as are, or have been Adverſaries of the good old government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Liturgy thereof, and have felt god's ſcourge heavie upon them; and thereby to ſtifle the noiſe of the Croaking Toads, that of late have been creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad to the diſparagement of the good old way of God's worſhip. But the truth is, by all theſe things 'tis hard to judge of god or evill, 'tis Turkiſh or Cromwellian divinity to judge of the right of a Religion, by the lives or events of thoſe that profeſs it; let Holy writ, as it is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the ancient Church, and Fathers, who were neareſt the Fountain be our guide, and never go to the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies of Enthuſiaſmes, and miſ-applyed providences, vvhich muſt needs miſ-lead us.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151108:5"/>
            <head>The true Copy of a Letter from a very Reverend Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in anſvver to a young man, who deſired his judgement, without delay, upon this Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether every Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> be bound in conſcience to read the Common-prayer?</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Receiv'd your Letter in <hi>folio,</hi> with others incloſed, which I have returned. The Books you write of, I have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; yet I thank you for your good intentions, I am ſorry the paper is printed by it ſelf; it will be the leſs publick, ſooner die, and vvill make the Authour the more enquired after, vvhich may prove prejudicial.</p>
            <p>Your Caſe, you ſent me, muſt be put thus; vvhether a Miniſter, that is, every Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (All indefinites <hi>in materiaâ neceſſariâ</hi> are equivalent to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſals) be bound in conſcience to uſe the Common prayer.</p>
            <p>The Caſe thus put, there ſeem many things to be ſaid to the contrary, <hi>E. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. No Miniſter is bound in conſcience to do any thing, which will be more hurtfull, then profitable to God's Church; but vve think this vvill be ſo, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2. No Miniſter is bound in conſcience to that vvhich will offend any godly men: but this vvill do ſo, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>3. No man is bound in conſcience to any thing forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by lavvfull Authority: But the Common-prayer was forbidden by Lords and Commons, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>4. That which hath been diſuſed, and ſo is antiquated, doth not binde without an Act of Reviver: The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer hath been thus diſuſed; and there is no ſuch Act, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151108:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151108:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151108:7"/>
               <item>5. Nothing can thus binde, which is not of faith; for what is not of faith is ſin: But thus to do, is not of faith to ſome, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>6. The Miniſter is not bound in conſcience to any thing, which will cauſe him to be ſuſpected of lightneſs; and ſo bring him and his Miniſtry into contempt with the people: But this will do ſo, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>7. He is not bound in his conſcience to do that, againſt which he hath ſhevved his diſlike, either by preaching, or conference with his people: But ſome Miniſters have done ſo; Therefore not lawful for them; or at leaſt they are not bound in conſcience, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c</item>
               <item>8. No man is bound in conſcience to any Act of impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which may make him ridiculous to others: But this may be ſuch; if there ſhould come from ſupream authority, either a prohibition or alteration of that ſervice; But, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>9. No man is bound in conſcience to that, from which he hath a diſpenſation from his lawfull Superiour: But ſome have been ſo diſpenſed with, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>10. None are bound to this, who was ordeined without Oathes and Subſcriptions: But ſome Miniſters have been ſo ordeined, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This is all you have in your paper, and all I think can be ſaid by others (which queſtion not the thing in it ſelf, as did the old Puritans, as unlawfull) for the Negative.</p>
            <p>For the Affirmative, it is ſaid,
<list>
                  <item>1. Every man is bound to that which the Law of the land ſtill in force require of him: But the Law of the land ſtill in force requires the reading of the Common-prayer, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>2. Every Miniſter is bound to what the Law of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151108:7"/>Church by her Canons and Conſtitutions requires of him: But, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. Every Miniſter is bound in conſcience to uſe that kind of publick worſhip (ſuppoſing neither reſtraint nor danger) which is beſt for the peoples edification, and for God's glory: But this is incomparably beſt for both theſe ends: except they will magnifie their own prayers, before and after Sermon, to be better; a phanſie eaſily to be refelled, <hi>Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>4. Every Miniſter is bound in conſcience, and, by all lawfull means to root out the memory of the late rebellion in the State, and confuſion in the Church: But the uſing of the Common prayer doth both theſe.
<list>
                        <item>1. Againſt the Presbyterians, who in <hi>Scotland</hi> began the War, becauſe the Common-prayer was there uſed.</item>
                        <item>2. Againſt the Browniſt, Anabaptiſt, Quaker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at home, whoſe greateſt hope was, by deſtroying both the doctrine and diſcipline of our Church, to bring in their own diſtractions, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Every Miniſter is bound in conſcience to declare his innocency, <hi>i.e.</hi> That he is not involved in the guilt of our former ſin againſt God, the King, the Church, the people of this Land, committed in the late troubles: But there is ſcarce any better way for him thus to clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, then by the uſing the Common-prayer, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>6. Every Miniſter is bound in conſcience to that which may beſt conduce to the Re-ſettlement of the Kingdom in peace: But the uſe of the Common-prayer, ſuppoſing it lawfull and good in it ſelf, is ſuch a way of ſettlement, <hi>&amp;c. Ergò,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>7. Every man is bound in Practicall duties, which are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151108:8"/>good and lawfull ſervices of God, to conform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the judgement and practice of the ſupream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, of the beſt learned in the Laws, of the beſt-able and moſt Divines, of the greater and more intelligent part of the Nobility, Gentry and people of the Nation, where he lives; elſe he cannot avoid the note either of peeviſh ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, or pride and ſchiſm: But the Common-prayer is the practice of the King in his Court, of the Inns of Court, the Univerfities, the beſt and ableſt Divines in the Countrey, &amp;c <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>8. Every Miniſter is bound in conſcience to free himſelf, from all juſt ſuſpition of Hypocriſie and diſsimulation, when he declares his judgement to be Epiſcopall: But the beſt or onely way to prove his ſincerity in this, is to uſe Common-prayer: for he that declares for the one, <hi>i.e.</hi> Epiſcopacy, and will not declare for, <hi>i.e.</hi> uſe the other, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in a manner contradictions. He cannot be <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Epiſcopall, that is not <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Liturgicall.</item>
                  <item>9. Every Miniſter is bound in conſcience to give his people all thoſe Holy things, which God and the Laws of the land, Civill and Eccleſiaſtical, make their due; and in ſuch manner, as is by both or either preſcribed; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when either the Whole, or the Majour, or any conſiderable part of them ſhall require them at his hand, elſe he is a defrauder, nay, ſacrilegious: But the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer is an Holy thing of God, by Law both divine and humane, made the peoples due; therefore, ſuppoſing they require it, he is bound in conſcience to give it them.</item>
                  <item>10. The Miniſter is bound in conſcience to go before the people in his congregation in publick worſhip: But without the Common-prayer, there is no publick worſhip, in the congregation: For reading of Scripture (which is very little
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151108:8"/>in uſe amongſt them, they will not allow for worſhip; The ſinging of a Pſalm out of the Book, is accepted little better; the Sermon is not worſhip; the Miniſter's prayer is his own, not the People's; and many times ſuch, as few, or none, can ſay Amen to. But in the Common Prayer, all ſorts of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are given to the God-head; and to every perſon ſingly and diſtinct; and ſuch as the people know, and wherein they can joyn, and whereunto they can, without ſcruple, ſay, Amen, &amp;c. <hi>Ergò, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of the Truth, in this caſe, we muſt diſtinguiſh, what we mean by Miniſters: For though the word be plaine of it ſelf, yet theſe times have made it equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocall.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Some are ſo only in Title, among the people where they live, but were never ordained; theſe be Theeves, that came not in by the Door, meer Intruders, worſe then the Mendicant Fryers amongſt the Papiſts: for theſe, though they are not ordained, have licence from the <hi>Pope,</hi> who confirmed their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Some were ordained by Presbyterie: theſe alſo are no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by the Accompt of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and muſt take their Ordination again from the Biſhops, if they meane to be accepted Miniſters in this Church. Not that we deny Ordination in Forreign parts, eſpecially, in <hi>France,</hi> where no Biſhops are, nor can be, with the allowance of the Supreame Magiſtrate; but becauſe our Lawes require, and have eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed that Ordination only. Therefore neither of theſe two ſorts of Miniſters are concerned in the Caſe: but it is only of Miniſters legally Ordained.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We muſt remember, how the conſcience is bound, and what is here meant thereby.</p>
            <p>The conſcience is bound two manner of wayes.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151108:9"/>
            <p n="1">1 Primarily, Immediately, Directly, from God himſelf, and that either by ſome Naturall Law, written in the heart, or ſome Poſitive Law, written in the Scripture; We underſtand it not in this ſenſe; the Miniſter is not ſo bound.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Conſcience is bound, but Mediately, and Indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when the Magiſtrate commands any thing which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: For the Subject's Conſcience is bound to the Law, though that Law do not binde it, being meerly Humane.</p>
            <p>It will not be amiſſe to adde a third Obligation which may lye upon the Conſcience, by way of conſequence. As when great Benefits have been received, we are by them bound in Conſcience. <hi>i.e.</hi> Equity and Reaſon to returne thanks, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, requitalls; and ſo ſome Expound <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Not only for fear, but Conſcience ſake.</hi> It is taken in theſe two laſt ſenſes in the Preſent caſe.</p>
            <p>The third thing to be obſerved is, what is meant by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Common-Prayer? whether it be meant in whole, or in part, alwaies, never miſſing, or ſometimes according to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and occurring circumſtances? And it is in this laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that here we take it: For it was in my memory once moved in convocation, and anſwer was given, That the Church intended not to make it a Drudgerie: If he that hath no Aſſiſtant, ſhould firſt read the firſt ſervice wholely, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Preach, and then again read the ſecond Service, it were an heavy burthen for the ſtrongeſt Lungs.</p>
            <p>The concluſion therefore is, that every Miniſter, legally Ordained, is bound in conſcience both mediately, and by way alſo of conſequence, to read the Common-Prayer, at Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if there be a Sermon; at other times wholly, as it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: And the arguments to the contrary do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, Neither Propoſition is true: Not the firſt;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151108:9"/>For the Miniſter, and every good man, is bound to do vvhat is his duty, vvhatſoever the event may be to others. I muſt preach the Word, though it prove to ſome the ſavour of death. I muſt Adminiſter the Sacrament, though ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver may eat his own Damnation. I muſt vvorſhip God in Publick, as the Magiſtrate commands me, though ſome receive hurt thereby. Good ought not to be overcome of Evill.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Propoſition is not true, nor is it ſo ſet down, but with a <hi>Putamus.</hi> We perhaps think otherwiſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if it do more harm then good, it's <hi>per Accidens;</hi> The hurt is not from any fault in the thing, but from the fault of thoſe that receive hurt by it. So Wine may be hurtful; and the Sun-ſhine, becauſe of vapours and noiſom weeds, exhaled by it from the earth, By the Church alſo in this Argument, is meant Some, <hi>i.e.</hi> a party in the Church, and ſo we have it in the ſecond Argument, which invalidates the force of them.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond Argument we ſay, That a Miniſter is bound in conſcience to do that which may offend ſome godly men, if it be an offence taken, not given. If a good thing be drawn by evil conſtruction to be made a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block, if the thing be a publick Duty, not a private Action, if thereupon ſome be offended at the doing; Others, and they much to be preferred, for Number, Wiſdome, Authority, be offended at the not doing; if a Reaſon be rendred to take off the offence, it ceaſeth to be <hi>Scandalum Puſillorum,</hi> and is become <hi>Scandalum Phariſaeorum,</hi> and then our Saviour's Rule takes place, <hi>Let them be offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the third, It was never forbidden by lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The Houſes made an Ordinance, that is no law. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Parliament are of force, but <hi>ſedente Parlamento.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151108:10"/>Thoſe that think otherwiſe of that Ordinance, and conclude it preſumption to go againſt it, are poor <hi>Ignaro's,</hi> and ought not to be humoured: For it is a part of the inflaming the Nation to obey Ordinances as Laws: He that humours them herein, is, if a knowing man, more guilty then they.</p>
            <p>To the fourth: the Propoſition is untrue. For though Time eats thorough all things, yet not Lawes; unleſſe by a very long diſuſing. It's not ſo here. Beſides, the diſuſe was by reaſon of force, or fear; ſuch diſuſe doth not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquate Lavves, but only a voluntary laying them aſide.</p>
            <p>To the Fifth: Faith in that of the Apoſtle, is nothing but a knowledge of the thing I do, to be lawfull: But to read the Common-Prayers to be lawfull, appears
<list>
                  <item>1 Becauſe we have proved it to be a neceſſary duty.</item>
                  <item>2 Becauſe it is not inexpedient, in regard of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or People; but moſt expedient for both; as the Arguments do ſhew.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To the Sixth. The Miniſter doth incurre thereby no ſuſpition of Levitie; but rather, he doth Proclaime his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, to the Law, to the Church, to his firſt Principles. If a Woman raviſhed from her lawfull Husband, for twelve years, ſhould take the firſt opportunitie to run from the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſher, to her firſt Husband, were ſhe to be judged light? So, &amp;c. They rather are to be condemned of lightneſſe, which have been carried from their firſt Principles, by every winde, and now are aſhamed to returne.</p>
            <p>To the ſeventh. The Propoſition is ſo falſe, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is moſt true: For Retractations of Errours, publickly broached, or privately inſtilled, are as neceſſary to a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as Repentance and Reſtitution are for Sinners: Elſe the Miniſter pretends to Lord it over God's People, as if he had the Pope's ſpirit of Infallibility. The Miniſter's hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151108:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſincerity, ſhould make him do in this; what the <hi>Pope</hi>'s pride, and ſelfe ends, ſuffer him not to do.</p>
            <p>To the Eighth. If a Prohibition, or Alteration of the Service, ſhould come from Authority: He were imprudent, and ridiculous, that ſhould afterwards uſe it: But to uſe it now, whileſt the law, binding thereto, is in force, were no more ridiculous (ſuppoſing ſuch Prohibition, or Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be ſo, then to obſerve, at preſent, any Law of the Land) which the State may think fit to diſanull. It would not be ridiculous; but only to men that are ridiculous.</p>
            <p>To the Nineth. No lawfull Superiour hath diſpenſed with any Miniſter; as is pretended. I am ſure, the King and Parliament have not: I am ſure, a Biſhop cannot: He can only Connive, which is not to Diſpenſe: Beſides, is that Biſhop in being? Is he your Biſhop? Will he own it? Perſonall Acts of this nature die, and become Null with the Perſon. This is two thin a Fig-leafe.</p>
            <p>To the Tenth. That ever Biſhop <hi>S.</hi> ordeined any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, without the Oaths of Allegiance, and Supremacy, and that of Canonicall Obedience; without ſubſcribing likewiſe to the Doctrine, and Diſcipline of the Church, <hi>Credat Judaeus.</hi> If they pleaſe, the Biſhop ſhall anſwer for himſelf: I will procure it.</p>
            <p>You ſee how willing I am to ſerve you; and howmuch I rely upon your wiſedome, and fidelitie, to betray theſe things into your hands. I pray remember, they are not to be communicated by tran-ſcribed Copies. You know they muſt needs be almoſt Extemporary Conceptions. I ſhould be unwilling to father ſuch Scribbles, yet they were ever my deſtiny. <hi>Odi puerum,</hi> you ſay, and I, <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum praecŏcis ingenii.</hi> Make what uſe you pleaſe of the thing, (if it be uſefull) but not of my Name. There is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151108:11"/>little hope of prevailing, with thoſe that are contrary mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; unleſſe Authority ſtip in: And there is as little in it, to confirme you in your practice of going to another Church. This is another Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> VVhether my own Miniſter, refuſing to do his duty, as he ought, by Law, to doe, I may forſake him, and the Congregation? Is not this alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of the Church, and State? Is it not to countenance the Schiſmaticks in their Separating? May it not ſeem to diſturbe be Churches peace? VVhat then is to be done?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Treat with him in all gentleneſſe, and meekneſſe, in private: for rebuke openly belongs to Authority.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this ſucceed not, then according to Chriſt's rule, take others with you. If that fayle, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae.</hi> If this may not at preſent be had, deſire his leave to be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Congregation, till a ſettlement, by order, be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>I muſt have this Copie again; for I have no other. It's fit I ſhould have a counterpart of all my deeds. But I hope, you will not think it worth your keeping. I beleeve, you will prove a bad Conjurer, All your ſpells will not ſend me to <hi>London,</hi> till the Convocation; if then: Againſt vvhich, as to my ovvn particular, <hi>I</hi> vvill as heartily pray, as <hi>I</hi> do novv reſiſt your exerciſeneſs. Thanks be to God, there be ſtore of my betters, much abler Penns, and Tongues; and thoſe alſo perſonally concerned. <hi>I</hi> am ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vvith this long Scribble; Read it as vvell as you can, and Command to Love, and Serve you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151108:11"/>
            <p>IN Anſwer to that part of this Letter, where the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend man caveats the young man that conſulted him, for going to another Church, where Common-prayer was, from his own Pariſh-Church, where it was not, The young man made this Reply, That though indeed, by the Lawes of the Realm, and the Church, neither he, nor any man, ſeem to be bound to go out of their ovvn Pariſh to Church, but may, if they pleaſe, ſerve God in their own Families; yet any man, as he conceived, might lawfully, and if with conveniency he could, ſhould do well, as vvell for good example. as that he might the more regularly worſhip God in publick, to reſort to ſome other Church, vvhere lavvful Divine Service vvas. And ſo much the Act for Uniformitie ſeems to exhort, if not, enjoyne, <hi>viz.</hi> That every man, unleſſe he hath a lavvful Excuſe, ought to be at his ovvn Pariſh-Church, or at ſome other, vvhere the Common prayer is.</p>
            <p>He likevviſe certified, That he had treated vvith the Reputed Miniſter of his ovvn Pariſh, vvith all gentleneſs, and meekneſs, in private; and yet that he thought, that Rebuke openly, by vvay of Fraternal Correption, and not as in an Authoritative vvay, might belong to any private Chriſtian: Onlie he muſt be ſure, to look vvell to it, That the Perſon he rebuked, vvere manifeſtlie, and notoriouſlie, a Breaker of ſome Lavv, as he conceived, the Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that did refuſe to uſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, to be. As for example, any private Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may rebuke one, that he ſees filching a yard of Ribbon or Tape, of a Rob-orchard; or in a thing more indifferent, for not ſtanding bare, or ſhevving due Reverence to the King, or any other of his Superiours, and conſequently,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151108:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151108:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151108:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151108:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151108:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>may, nay, ought much more to rebuke openly, with the aboveſaid Reſtriction, Him, that by his contempt or neglect of his Sovereigns Injunctions, by Law, for the good and peace of the Church, ſhould merit it. He moreover repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Reverend man, that He, according to Chriſts Rule, before this intimation, had offered, nay preſſed for a conference with his Reputed paſtour, with, and before two other Miniſters; which was very hardly yielded to, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one of them, though both learned and Pious, had been a ſequeſtred man, yet ſuch were the unavoidable occaſions of the ſaid two Miniſters, that in diverſe weeks, yea, ſome moneths together, they could not be both at home at the ſame time, and ſo that conference as yet Uncompaſſed. For the <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> that then in the moſt received ſenſe, being then not to be had, the young man did deſire his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Paſtour's leave to be of another congregation; at which he was ſilent, and that the young man took for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and accordingly joyned himſelf to another congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about half a mile off; though thither he could not paſs in quiet without baſe reproaches, from the Diſciples of Him that would not perform Divine ſervice, according to Law. So that to ſuch a ſad paſs were things brought, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſties return to the exerciſe of his Regal office a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, That thoſe that would ſerve God regularly, and according to the eſtabliſhed Laws of the Church, and Kingdom, were fain to ſneak to it like Quakers, as if they onely vvere the Phanaticks, that obeyed authority, and thoſe, The onelie or the beſt Chriſtians in moſt places, that did leaſt conform themſelves thereto.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:151108:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter ſent from an Aſſociatour in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> who, for a while, boggled at the Common-prayer, but after was convinc'd of his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to another of the ſame Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not yet ſo convinc'd.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M. B.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>UNderstanding, that as yet you do forbear to uſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, and preſuming that you have not appear'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, I have taken the boldneſſe to offer you theſe Reaſons, why deferring any longer, that Work will not be expedient for our Church, as the Caſe now ſtands.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The reſtraint being taken off, that hindered the exerciſe of that Service; that 'tis expected we ſhould obey the Law in force, appears by the Examples both of the King and Parliament, and the new printing of the Service-books, againſt the last Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving day, with ſome Prayers added for that ſeaſon; which I have ſeen.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Your Example retards others; which perhaps is diſcerned by others better then by your ſelf, they having therefore a greater eſteem of you, becauſe they judge you vile in their own eyes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The people do generally forſake thoſe Churches where 'tis not uſed; and the far greater part of the Nation are for it; which (ſuppoſing the lawfulneſſe of the thing) is reaſon enough. For if there be a neceſſity of offending one ſide, <hi>in Licitis,</hi> the Rule is, we must reſpect the greater part in the firſt place; but then, if thoſe <hi>Licita,</hi> be alſo commanded by a Law in force, I ſee no Plea can be made againſt them</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> 'Tis time, after all our high flights, to ſtoop to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the people; the generality are ſo dull, that they cannot follow their Leaders, who are too nimble for them. Therefore, the ſheep do chooſe rather to follow the lame Shepherd, whoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151108:15"/>pace is moſt ſuitable to their ſlowneſs, and apply themſelves to the plaineſt, and moſt homely prayers, as moſt agreeable to their Capacities.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Stronger Chriſtians, as they abound in gifts and parts, ſo they ſhould with charity, and for the weak brother's ſake, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent therewith.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> We cannot well anſwer the Objection of Schiſm from the Papiſts, if we depart from them, where there is no neceſsity: much leſſe, if we renounce the Common Prayer, becauſe, as ſome alledge, taken out of theirs. This Sophiſme uſed to make the people hate it, is indeed a ſolid reaſon to make men of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding love it, as Gold refined from droſſe: and implying a charitable deſire of Communion with them, wherein we may.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Since the laying aſide of the Liturgie, and our Diſcipline, Popery has gotten much ground; and many went over to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſeeing our diſagreement in every thing, Creed, Prayers, Baptiſme, Catechiſme, Euchariſt, Marriage, Burial, Viſitation of the ſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which is ſolved by the old way, and Diſcipline: and while every one purſued his own way, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable was the ſcandal.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> Wiſe men have thought it the beſt way to preſerve a State, to reduce it to it's principles, by which it grew great (as <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> notes concerning Catechiſm:) and this is that which is now doing in the Civil body, proportionably ſo ſhould it be in the Church, (for the Vine thrives and grows with the Elme.) How ſhall all theſe Extravagancies be cured? but by reſuming that way, wherein we may (thoſe things being removed that are juſtly offenſive) walk orderly, unanimouſly and ſoberly, and if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be well examin'd, more profitably to the common Intereſt of the Church, in charity and union; and though knowledge and gifts may have increaſed more by the new way, yet theſe alſo are not hindred by the old.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> Equity; and Reaſon, and the Law of Nations, do favour that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151108:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>in Being, till orderly judgement of Deciſion be given againſt it: Are we not bound then to ſuſpend our Reaſons, inducing us to think hardly of the Liturgie, ſpecially if not demonstrative: Or elſe we trouble the Church without neceſsity: But 'tis objected, that it has been condemned already by the moſt godly and zealous, <hi>&amp;c. Anſ.</hi> It was never condemned in an orderly way. A Bias of Partiality was apparent, in that they never admitted them to conſultation who ſtood for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>10.</hi> All exceptions against our Liturgie, muſt either be againſt a Set-form in general, or againſt This form. To the first, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, The ſpecial ſacerdotal Benediction, and decimal profeſsion, were deliver'd, in an expreſſe forme; and the Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> of which St. <hi>Jerome</hi> has obſerved foure to be intitled prayers, were ſtanding parts of the Jewiſh Liturgy. The <hi>70.</hi> Diſciples were all to uſe one ſhort Benediction, when ſent to preach the Goſpell. <hi>Luke</hi> the <hi>10.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> concludes almoſt all his Epistles with one ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. <hi>Juſtine Martyr,</hi> one of the eldest Sons of the Church, mentions <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> And the ſame we have in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who has left us heads of prayer for their Emperours, <hi>vitam prolixam, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tutam, ſenatum fidelem,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, compoſed with study. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Euſeb.</hi> which is, as I conceive, He duely ſaid his Set and Appointed prayers with his houſhold.</p>
            <p>As for this forme, that our Church uſes, our <hi>Hooker</hi> has long ſince at large aſſerted it, with ſuch arguments, as may be enough to caution a moderate and peaceable man, to be very tender, and wary, how he oppoſes his Private, to the Publick judgment of the Church, though he be not fully ſatisfied in every particular: Adde to this, that our Liturgie, had the approbation of <hi>Calvin,</hi> whoſe judgment in other things is of very great weight with us: Worthy Sir, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming on your goodneſſe, I have made bold to offer theſe Reaſons to you, which if they prevaile not with you, yet may be a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my obſervance, and reſpects to you.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>July <hi>the 20. 1660.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>Your unworthy fellow-labourer in the Miniſtry. <hi>C M.</hi>
               </signed>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151108:16"/>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>To this Letter, the over-grave Gentleman gave only this Anſvver, to the Endighter of it, though, no vvhit inferior to him in age, degree, or ſtanding in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> but his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior in all thoſe reſpects, but very magiſterially thus, or very neer to this purpoſe, and in as fevv vvords. Sir, I thank you for your Letter, but there vvere ſome miſtakes in it. But vvhere, or hovv, his ſeraphicalneſſe vvould not vouchſafe to ſhevv.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Communicating the above-ſaid Letter, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Papers to that Reverend Perſon, who ſtated the Caſe afore recited, was returned this brief Anſwer following.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu muſt not be offended, if I anſwer your <hi>Folio</hi> in this <hi>Decimo ſexto.</hi> I have peruſed your Chartar, your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, opinion, your Scholars gloſſe upon it; my judgment is in brief; Go on, and proſper. To me the Chartar is expreſs, the counſells opinion clear for you; and many caſes in the printed Book come home: and <hi>I</hi> obſerve all the Deciſions are more then ordinarily favourable to your pious uſe. I cannot believe (whatſoever is pretended to the contrary) but that your Governours will be found to ſtand in a double capacitie. 1. As Governours. 2. As Feoffees, and ſo queſtionable, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they might without fear, either keep all to themſelves, or ſell the Lands to others, without controule.</p>
            <p>I thank you for your Letter newes, though nothing in them comes up to my expectation. Biſhops, Deans, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, are ſettled, but no Vote for Church Lands. Will they leave them to the Law? When they did not the King. And will not, as it ſeemes by Coll. <hi>Kings</hi> Petition, leave to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151108:16"/>the Law, thoſe that have ſequeſtred Miniſters; nor do ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred Gentlemen returne to their Eſtates by Law. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reconcile this</p>
            <p>That Dr. <hi>W.</hi> ſhould be a Biſhop, is not beyond my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, nor that he gives you ſo faire an invitation: only I think that a good Parſonage in <hi>England,</hi> is better then a Dean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery in <hi>Ireland.</hi> I am glad to hear that Dr. <hi>H.</hi> is of Sarum; but ſtand at gaze to hear that my antient Friend Dr. <hi>Sb.</hi> ſhall be of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> I attribute it to <hi>Dr. St.</hi> They were <hi>ex Intimis. I</hi> am glad Mr. <hi>M.</hi> comes off, and labours to draw after him <hi>Arietem gregis;</hi> but, <hi>I</hi> beleeve, in vayne: For the man, I beleeve, is now dyed in graine, and thinks the whole ſervice unlawfull; though he pretend diſuſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation, offence, &amp;c. Mr. <hi>M.</hi> doth court him hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, with high flights, and ſtooping, &amp;c. But I hope, he meanes, Ironically. All their high flights being like thoſe of the <hi>Swallowes</hi> in foggy weather, which are as low as the Earth it ſelf, when they hunt for flies. I wiſh he had man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged his Argument of Schiſmes in another vvay. He ſaith from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt vvhich perhaps Mr. <hi>B.</hi> thinks it impoſſible to be a Schiſmatick. But I vvould have ſaid, from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Nor do I commend his argument from the grovving of Popery; vvhich, <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, vvas not from the diſuſe of the Service, but from abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing Biſhops and the Diſcipline, and a vvorld of learned men vvith them. And to conclude, notvvithſtanding all your Magical malice, I am ſure to be ſafe till <hi>October:</hi> In the vvhile, if you think any thing conſiderable, vvrite to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Friend</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Your Papers are in your Chartar.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151108:17"/>
            <p>TO Conclude theſe Diſcourſes, 'tvvill not be amiſſe to adde one ſeaſonable Exhortation, to all ſuch as are ill-affected to the old Government of the Church, by Biſhops, and the Publick Divine Service, by the Liturgie, that are not contented to worſhip God, and hear his holy Writt, read, expounded, or preach't, at the Canonical houres in Churches; and to pray, and reade the Bible at due times in their own Families, beſides their Cloſet or private Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and occaſional good Conferences, that they may finde opportunities for, as they ride, or walk, or otherwiſe regularly converſe with others, as they be going about their other lawful occaſions, but muſt needs have, and by no Prohibition of the Laws of the Realm, and the Church, will forbear their riotous meetings, unlavvful Aſſemblies and Conventicles, in and by which principally, the late hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Rebellion was hatcht.</p>
            <p>Let them but ſeriouſly reflect upon the paſt troubles and the firſt Riſe of them; and make impartial enquirie, vvhether or no all thoſe, and only thoſe, that vvere for ſuch Conventicles, and Deſpiſers of the Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Liturgie, vvere not thoſe that made up the firſt Army, that Rebell'd againſt the King, Robbed Churches, Seized on other mens eſtates, and out of whom are ſpaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all the Phanaticks of latter dayes.</p>
            <p>They ſeriouſly conſidered, and found true, which will eaſily be, if in every Town or Pariſh a ſlight kenne be taken, one would think it ſufficient to make every ſober minded perſon to repent heartily, if he be guilty in this kind, and after ſo much mercy from ſo gracious a Prince, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how he be found faultie, by countenancing or fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting ſuch unlawful Aſſemblies, or Conventicles: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much mercy, I ſay, of ſo gracious a Prince, who, as a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151108:17"/>Rank Phancie did expreſſe it t'other day, hath in ſome ſenſe been more merciful, then God Almighty hath ever given us hope he will be, toward thoſe that treſpaſſe againſt him. For God never did, nor ever will forgive any that repent not, and make no reſtitution. But his Majeſtie hath forgiven hundreds, nay, thouſands, I doubt, milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that never truly repented of their treſpaſſe againſt Him, and his Father, of bleſſed memory; and for ought that yet appears, intend no reſtitution. 'T were to be wiſht they would conſult their beloved Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> &amp;c. and then anſwer this Queſtion, <hi>viz. VVhether they be not bound in Conſcience to make Reſtitution to thoſe they have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to their utmoſt ability, if ever they hope for Heaven, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Kings Act of Oblivion, which abſolves them only</hi> in Foro Humano, <hi>not</hi> in Foro Conſcientiae.</p>
            <p>But it is too too Apparent, how farre from any ſuch Act as this, nay, how Diabolically malicious ſome Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts and Phanaticks be, if they cannot compaſſe their irregular deſignes, by a late Horrid ſlaunder, that an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, more then Treble Turn-coat wretch, the other day forged againſt the Reverend Father in God, the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells;</hi> not ſticking to brand him, in the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of one of the moſt eminent perſons in the Nation, for an old Leacher or Goat, as the vile foul-mouth expreſt it, affirming, That the good old Father, who is now in his fourſcorth year, and even bowed together with age, was a moſt inſatiate effeminate perſon, and had lately married a young wench of one or two and twenty, and yet was not ſatisfied with her, but neighed after other women. Now all this Helliſh Aſperſion was raiſed upon no other ground, but becauſe the ſaid vile wretch, a vertiginous Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel forſooth, of the worſt ſtamp; could not wreſt out of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151108:18"/>the ſaid Reverend Biſhops hands, one of the beſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, belonging to the See of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi> But the Biſhop being, as was ſaid, now in his eightieth year; and his ſecond wife, whom he married about foure or five years ſince, for a Nurſe and Comfort in his diſconſolate conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being a very grave Matron of ſixty years of Age; what ſpark of Probability, or ground for ſuch a baſe ſlander there could be, let all candid Chriſtians judge, to whom the Reverend Father does appeal; and the ſame Father is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take an Oath, with ſuch an Awful Execration, for his purgation in that particular, that his ſlanderers dare not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him therein. Yet what if an Ancient Biſhop or Churchman had indeed taken a young <hi>Abiſhag</hi> in the way of Matrimony, to comfort and cheriſh him in his old age; as <hi>David</hi> did, without it, had it been ſuch an abominable thing? The truth is, too many of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobilitie and Gentry, as vvell as the Commonaltie, do ſpeak too vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Gods Ordinance, Matrimony, eſpecially in the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, as if they did more then encline to Poperie in that point; And ſome coy Ladies, that think it a fine thing to have a ſpruce Chaplain to vvait upon them, in a little higher Sphere then a Serving-man, do even vomit to hear of the marriage of a bavvdy Prieſt, as they moſt unchriſtianly ſpeak, as if they honoured neither God, nor his Chriſt, ſo much as <hi>Ethnicks</hi> honour'd their falſe gods, and their Prieſts for their ſakes. Hovv frequent is it vvith the moſt, to make a ſcorn in all companies of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him Parſon, Parſon, at every turne, not in Reſpect, but in baſe contempt. Which vvord hath too long, and yet doth continue, to be in as great deriſion, as of late the name of King, Duke, Earle, Lord, or Biſhop. And vvhat mocks and flouts are daily, and hourely, caſt at the Regular
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151108:18"/>Clergie, as they paſſe in the ſtreets, and even in ſome of the moſt Eminent Noble Families in and about <hi>London,</hi> 'tis a ſhame to hear and ſee. And if his Majeſtie, and other Noble Perſonages, do not ſpeedily declare in their Families, and elſewhere, their deteſtation of ſuch ſcornes, and give open countenance to thoſe that are ſet apart for God's Service, as well as to that Worſhip by Common prayer, eſtabliſhed by Law, 'tis to be feared, that all our old Animoſities will ferment to that height, that 'twill be too late to ſuppreſſe them.</p>
            <p>'Twas ſome few daies ago ſpoken in no leſſe a family, then the Lord Generall's, by a Majors wife, who may be ſuppoſed to ſpeak the ſenſe of her husband, and of divers others of that gang, that the Kings Quire, were no better then a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Fidlers, and that ſhe hoped to live to ſee all ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious fooleries, pulled down with a vengeance, and to have thoſe that love to go in long Garments, and yet were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Wolves in Sheeps clothing, to beſtript of their forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and that ſhe knew there were thouſands, nay, millions in the three Nations of her minde. The reaſon why this is here inſerted, is, that if poſſible, ſome notice of ſuch ſeditious ſpirits may come to his Majeſties, and the Lord General's eares, and be ſpeedily checkt.</p>
            <p>That ſlander lately raiſed againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> is much like that other of old forged, and in all Pulpits of the Non-conformiſts moſt impudently, as groſſe a lie as it is, proclaimed, to make him, and that whole order odious, <hi>viz.</hi> That he ſhould ſay, that he thanked God, he had left never a Lecturer in his whole Dioceſſe. Whereas there is not a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of any Intelligence, that lived in that Dioceſſe, but knowes, that there were continually, as learned Lectures of Reverend men, with the approbation of the ſaid Biſhop, in the ſaid Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151108:19"/>as in any other. Indeed that prudent Governour of the Church, was, and is, ſomewhat of Sir <hi>Henry Wootton's,</hi> or rather of <hi>Lipſius</hi> his opinion, that not only <hi>Diſputandi,</hi> but alſo <hi>Praedicandi pruritus fit Eccleſiae ſcabies;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did his endeavour to ſuppreſſe, and hinder the placing of ſingle Lecturers in Cities, Townes, and Villages, by any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the people, without, and againſt the good liking of the lawfull Rector, or Incumbent. And how many are there, that were the greateſt followers, and admirers, of ſuch ſingle factious Lecturers, that are now convinc'd, that they were the bellowes, that blew up the flame, that hath ſo long waſted both Church, and State. And indeed ſuch is imprudence, and paſſion, of many Preachers, that wiſe men conceive Sir <hi>Francis Bacon's</hi> propoſal, not without very good reaſon; and that it would tend more to the Churches peace, and the good of ſouls, if there were one compleat body of wholeſome Homilies, or Sermons, one, or two, for every Lord's day, and other Feſtivalls thorowout the whole year; compoſed, or collected, by the moſt learned, and pious of our Church, and ſet out by Authority to be read to the people, in ſtead of ſo many Crude Rhapſodies; as are many times through haſte, or want of learning, and prudence, obtruded on them. And that only ſome few that are known to be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and of a right ſober, and peaceable temper, upon very ſpeciall occaſions, or emergencies, ſhould be allowed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Prayers, or Sermons, of their own; and thoſe likewiſe to be well ſcanned by ſome in Authority, before they be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in publick. The very Poets, and Oratours, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the antient <hi>Ethnicks,</hi> took this care, before they did dare to commit any thing to publick view, or audience, not only for the propriety, and puritie of the words, and phraſe, but alſo for the ſoliditie, and pertinencie's ſake, of what they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151108:19"/>penned, as the Illuſtrious <hi>Lipſius,</hi> and ſince him, the learned <hi>Voſſius</hi> ſhew in their treatiſes <hi>de Recitatione veterum.</hi> And ſhall Heathens be more tender of their credits, then we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of the peace of the Church, and of Charity?</p>
            <p>I know nothing has conduced ſo much to the bringing us into thoſe late horrid confuſions, and ſo likely to hurry us back again into them, as that overweening Enthuſiaſticall opinion, which the common people have got among them, <hi>viz.</hi> That when a man is got up into the Pulpit, eſpecially, if he make uſe of no Notes, he has a ſpeciall, extraordinary inſpiration, not much ſhort of, if not the very ſame, with that of the old Prophets, Evangeliſts, and Apoſtles; and that God puts even the words, and phraſes, into his minde, and mouth, and that what he there prayes, and preaches, as they call it, is the very word of God, farre tranſcending that which is read in the Pew below. The occaſion, or cauſe rather of this opinion among people, is, that this, and the like prefaces, are ordinarily recited in the Pulpit, never in the Pew, <hi>viz.</hi> Hearken to the word of God, as you ſhall finde it written, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or, hearken to the good word of God, as it ſhall be delivered to you, upon theſe words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or, give good heed, or attention, to the whole minde of God, as it ſhall be exhibited from theſe words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas alas, too too often, to the great grief of ſober minded Chriſtians, ſome are ſo far from giving the minde of God, that they do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the minde of learned men, upon thoſe places they undertake to handle.</p>
            <p>What if a man ſhould ſay, that ſince the death of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Evangeliſts, and Apoſtles, there is no preaching at all, properly, and ſtrictly ſo called? For they were the only proper <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> Heralds, Proclaimers, Predicatours, or, Embaſſadours, that brought the ſacred Meſſages to us im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151108:20"/>from God; and the Miniſters of the Goſpell now are bound up to their Canon, may not adde or diminiſh one <hi>Iota;</hi> and therefore are rather Expoſitours, then Preachers, unleſs it be in a very large, and improper ſenſe.</p>
            <p>What if a man ſhould ſay, that the expounding of any place of Scripture, muſt be done in the ſame way, and by the ſame helps, that a Maſter, or Uſher in a School, uſes in the expoſition of <hi>Iſocrates</hi> his <hi>Paraeneſis,</hi> or <hi>Tullie's</hi> Offices, or any other Claſſicall Author.</p>
            <p>What if a man ſhould ſay, that publick praying, or preaching in a large ſenſe, <hi>ex tempore,</hi> if any be ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely raſh and ſinfull, as ſo to do, (for ſome that are thought by the Deluded people ſo to do, do nothing leſs; but do make as many wry mouths &amp; cloſe-ſtool faces in private, to prepare thoſe crudities, as they do in ſqueezing them out in publick) is no more then for a ſchool-boy to make a rude Theam, Oration, or Verſe <hi>ex tempore.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, that praying and preaching, ſtill I mean in the larger ſenſe, are Acts converſant about ſacred things, and yet are no more properly gifts, then any of the liberall ſciences. God's good bleſsing no doubt does go along with them, where they are ſoberly and Regularly uſed, in their kinde; and ſo it doth with a chriſtian ſcholar or ſtudent in his other learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in it's kinde: And any one in the Pulpit, if he hath not read much, and ſtudied hard before hand, may as ſoon miſtake the true ſenſe of a place of Scripture, or faulter in his prayer, as a ſchool-maſter or ſcholar at the Desk or Table, if they be not circumſpect, in expounding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing, or parſing an Authour, or compoſing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing, Theam, Verſe or Oration.</p>
            <p>And this I take to be correſpondent to the mind of that Illuſtrious light of our Church, Doctor <hi>Hammond,</hi> in his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151108:20"/>preface to his precious Annotations upon the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and of all the moſt pious and learned Church-men of our Nation: who are content with that Honour which God hath given them, by an ordinary call, and his ordinary Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, without deſiring to boy upthemſelves in the eſteem of the Vulgar, by a Pretence to ſuch Mountebank Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſmes, as others boaſt of.</p>
            <p>And for the Specialties or particular Bills, that are put up in ſome of our Churches, it were well if they were a little better conſidered of, and whither they tend. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if a Lace-maker, or Button-ſeller, hath occaſion to go to a Faire or Market, at thirty o fourty miles diſtance, or to place a Boy to School, or an Apprentice, the Prayers of the greateſt Congregations are olemnly deſired for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Journey and Under taking. 'Tis true, God's Providence is over the meaneſt thing, and the loweſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, as over the very Sparrows, and the very hairs of our heads; and yet if a Sparrow, that one loves, ſhould be ſick, or ones haire begin to fal off, were it fit to put up a particular, publike, ſolemn prayer in a Church for them.</p>
            <p>What will wiſe men ſay to this Bill, <hi>viz. A Servant that is fallen into a prophane Familie, deſires the Prayers of this Congregation, that God would be peaſed in mercy, by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to finde out a way to remove him out of that Familie.</hi> Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I pray, tends this, but to faction and ſedition in Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as well as in the Church and State? One would have thought, if it had been fit at all, that ſuch a thing ſhould be put up in a Bill for publick Prayer, it ſhould rather have been thus, <hi>viz.</hi> A Servant that is fallen into a prophane Familie, deſires the prayers of this Congregation, that God would give him patience to continue there, and be a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to that Familie, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was to <hi>Potiphar</hi>'s, and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151108:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151108:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151108:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>for God's glory, by his good example.</p>
            <p>But ſhould we tell of all the ſtrange Extravagancies of ſome men, in their praying, preaching, thankſgivings and faſtings, as how one deſires God to make the King truly a Defender of the Faith; as if it were not his legal Title, and an Injunction of both Houſes, that he ſhould be prayed for as Defender of the Faith, truly Ancient, Catholick, and Apoſtolick, and in all Cauſes, and over all Perſons, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Temporal, in his Majeſties Realmes and Dominions, Supreme Head and Governour. But ſome men fondly think, if his Majeſtie be not for Presbyterie or Independencie, againſt Biſhops and Common-prayer, he cannot be truly a Defender of the Faith. Another appoints a publick Faſt of his private phancie; and prayes, that God would humble the Nation for not ſticking cloſe to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for ſtarting aſide from the Covenant, for not Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the Covenant, in it's principal and main ends and intentions. Another begs God to undermine and pull down the great ones in the Nation, that are combining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and Jeſus Chriſt, and the Power of Godlineſſe in the Nation, and that he would ſet up his <hi>Zerubbabels</hi> again in the Nation. Another preaches, that a true Miniſter of the Goſpel muſt uſe Diſtraction in his preaching, and not ſuch a kind of general preaching, as was now coming up in the Nation, which would break no bones, and convert no ſoules. Hath his Majeſtie been ſo gracious, as to forgive ſo much; and to declare for a warning his Reſolvedneſſe to uſe all rigour, and ſeverity, for the future, againſt all ſuch, as by word, or deed, ſhall do any thing contrary to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which comprehends as well that in the Church, as that in the State; and yet dare theſe Audacious Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſtill go on, under a pretence of zeal for God's glory, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151108:22"/>blow the Trumpet of Sedition, and another Rebellion? Let them take heed, that the hand of God, and Juſtice do not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake them, e're they be aware, as it hath ſome of their wicked crew.</p>
            <p>The Reader is deſired to take notice, that whereas there is a ſcandalous ſtory graſſant in diſhonour to the Reverend Biſhops, and Doctours of our Church, <hi>viz.</hi> That when the firſt newes of the Parliament's due ſubmiſſion to, and cloſe with his Majeſtie's Gracious declaration, was brought to the <hi>Hague;</hi> His Majeſty ſhould call upon a Biſhop or Doctour then preſent, in theſe, or ſuch like words. Come Doctour, ſince it hath pleaſed God, to be ſo Gracious to me, and my people, let Us immediately give God ſolemn thanks here, while the Commiſſioners be preſent. At which the Biſhop, or Doctour, was much abaſhed, as the ſtory runs, and making ſhift for a Common-prayer-book, did tumble it, and fumble it a long time, for ſome forme, or formes, to ſerve the particular occaſion; but after long ado, his Majeſty, with ſome paſſion ſaid, Why, cannot you give God thanks upon ſuch an eminent occaſion, without your Book? To which the Biſhop, or Doctour replied, may it pleaſe your Majeſty, I deſire not to be wiſer then the Church At which, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty haſtily ſnatcht the Book from him, laid it under his own Armes, and gave God thanks <hi>ex tempore,</hi> in an admirable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. This is the ſtory; but upon good enquirie, and diſcourſe with ſundry Perſons then preſent, it appears to be indeed but a ſtory; and if it be otherwiſe, let any of that gang diſprove it, if he can, in the next Pamphlet, or Journall. Doctour <hi>Earle,</hi> and Doctour <hi>George Hall,</hi> are Perſons <hi>fide digni,</hi> and were preſent, all the while the Commiſſioners were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Meſſage to the King; and they have been talked with, and averr the contrary. And no queſtion, His Majeſty,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151108:23"/>if he be humbly asked, will make good what they averr.</p>
            <p>VVell fare Mr. <hi>Faireclough</hi> of <hi>Wells</hi> in <hi>Somerſett,</hi> who hath the Knack of praying <hi>Ex tempore,</hi> as well as the beſt of them, and hath gone for a Presbyterian, that at a friendly Conference with ſome Divines in <hi>Dorſetſhire;</hi> ingenuouſly confeſſed, That he never prayed ſo heartily in his life, as at <hi>Cambridge</hi> by the Common-prayer. And that rather then there ſhould be another ſuch a Confuſion in Church or State, he could wiſh all the Presbyterians and Independents in <hi>England</hi> baniſht.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151108:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
